Register of the James A. Rabbitt Papers, 1895-1969
Hoover Institution Archives
James A. Rabbitt Papers,
1895-1969
71005
Rabbitt, James Aloysius, 1877-1969
61 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (26.35 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, memoirs, lectures, reports, surveys, patents, clippings, sketches, and photographs, relating to economic, scientific, and technological developments in the mining and metallurgical industries of China, Japan, and the Far East, with emphasis on nickel alloys, China labor and dockyard projects, cultivation of rice in Japan, and related governmental policies of China and Japan.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1971.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Agriculture--Japan; Engineering--China; Mines and mineral resources--China; Mines and mineral resources--East Asia; Mines and mineral resources--Japan; Nickel mines and mining; China; East Asia; Japan; Engineers
Container List
- Journal, 1913. (Box 1)
- Daybook, 1918.
- General correspondence - 1901, 1903, 1909-1910, 1912, 1914 1916.
- Correspondence, Rabbitt to Roland S. Morris, 1918-1919 re control of exports to Japan.
- Correspondence, A-B - 1930-1931. (Box 2)
- Correspondence, C-H - 1930-1931.
- Correspondence, I - 1930-1931. (Box 3)
- Correspondence, J-M - 1930-1931.
- Correspondence, N - 1930-1931. (Box 4)
- Correspondence, O-Z - 1930-1931.
- Correspondence, - 1932. (Box 5)
- Correspondence, May-December 1932 - Chronological outward file.
- Correspondence, 1932-1933.
- Correspondence, 1932-1933, general and legal between J. A. Rabbitt and Mitsui Company, Ltd. Japan re commercial agreements. (Box 6)
- Correspondence, 1932, between J. A. Rabbitt and Asano Bussan Company, Japan, re termination of trade with Asano.
- Correspondence, January-June, 1933 - Chronological outward file. (Box 7)
- Correspondence, July-December, 1933 - Chronological outward file.
- Correspondence, 1933, re China chemical industries and nickel agency in Manchuria. Also some Japanese agency correspondence. (Box 8)
- Correspondence, American European trip, 1934.
- Correspondence, 1934 - Chronological file. (Box 9)
- Correspondence, 1935 - Chronological commercial file.
- Correspondence, A-Z - 1935, commercial.
- Correspondence, 1936 - Chronological commercial file.
- Correspondence, A-L - 1936, American European trip. (Box 10)
- Correspondence, Mitsui-Z - 1936, American European trip. (Box 11)
- Correspondence, 1937 - Commercial chronological file.
- Correspondence, A-Z - 1937. (Box 12)
- Correspondence, 1938 - Commercial chronological file.
- Correspondence, A-Z - 1939.
- Correspondence, 1939 - Commercial chronological file. (Box 13)
- Correspondence, 1942; 1948-1951. (Box 14)
- Correspondence, 1948-1952.
- Engineering career 1902-1955, 1 folder. (Box 15)
- General career material, 1 folder.
- General career material, 1 scrapbook.
- Outline draft material for a biography entitled Yankee Engineer in Asia.
- Material for a biography entitled Yankee Engineer in Asia. 23 vols. as follows (this material is comprised mainly of daily business correspondence): (Box 16)
  - Volume 1, 1885-1902 - Missing.
  - Volume 2, 1902-1917 - Folder I.
  - Volume 2, 1902-1917 - Folder II. Includes patents data - aeroplane, talking machine motor, improvement of tires.
  - Volume 3, 1918-1920 - Folder I. (Box 17)
  - Volume 3, 1918-1920 - Folder II.
  - Volume 4, 1920-1922 - Folder I. (Box 18)
  - Volume 4, 1920-1922 - Folder II.
  - Volume 5, 1923-1924 - Folder I. (Box 19)
  - Volume 5, 1923-1924 - Folder II.
  - Volume 6, 1925-1929. (Box 20)
  - Volume 7, 1929-1931.
  - Volume 8, 1931-1941 - Folder I.
  - Volume 8, 1931-1941 - Folder II. (Box 21)
  - Volume 8, 1931-1941 - Folder III.
  - Volume 9, 1942-1944.
  - Volumes 10-11, 1945-1949.
  - Volume 12, 1950-1952. (Box 22)
  - Volume 13, 1952-1969 - Correspondence.
  - Volume 14 - Missing.
  - Volume 15 - Missing.
  - Volumes 16-17, ca. 1923 - China and Japan newspaper clippings.
  - Volume 18, 1921-1923 - Canton newsclippings re Sun Yat-sen.
  - Same as 36 f., 1922-1923.
  - Same as 36 g. (Box 23)
  - Same as 37 a.
  - Volume 19 - Missing.
  - Volume 19 - Missing.
  - Volume 21, ca. 1922, China projects, correspondence: Charter for Canton outer harbor and dockyard project; Proposed change in railway building policy, government of the province of Kwangtung, China; Kwangtung Provincial Service Commission. (Box 24)
  - Volumes 22-23, 1921-1924 - 4 folders. J. A. Rabbitt Engineering Corporation - correspondence and papers.
- Short stories, articles, and lectures by J. A. Rabbitt: (Box 25)
  - Prolonged Youth.
  - Tea Leaves - Philosophy of a Yankee Engineer.
  - Why I Like Japan.
  - History of Japan Under the Shoguns, 1603-1868.
  - Historical Background of Government in Japan, April 1941.
    - The Economic Orientation of the Far-Eastern Crisis, July-August, 1941, (file marked confidential). (Box 26)
    - Economic studies of Japan, China, and the Far East.
    - Mining and Metallurgy of Nickel.
    - Asis's Industrial Potential: A Survey (folder 1).
    - Asia's Industrial Potential: A Survey (folder 1). (Box 27)
    - Asia's Industrial Potential: A Survey (copy 2).
    - Australia's Industrial Potential: A Survey.
    - China's Industrial Potential: A Survey (folder 1). (Box 28)
    - China's Industrial Potential: A Survey (appendices - folder 2).
    - Formosa and Korea's Industrial Potential: A Survey.
    - India's Industrial Potential: A Survey.
    - Japan's Industrial Potential: A Survey (Volume 1). (Box 29)
    - Japan's Industrial Potential: A Survey (Volume 2).
    - Southeast Asia's Industrial Potential: A Survey - French Indo-China; Netherlands East Indies; Java; Malaysia; Siam. (Box 30)
    - Southwest Asia's Industrial Potential: A Survey.
    - Philippine's Industrial Potential.
    - Soviet Union Industrial Potential: A Survey (Volume 1).
    - Soviet Union Industrial Potential: A Survey (Volume 2).
    - Japan's Economic Position. (Box 31)
    - Japan Food Review.
    - Nickel and Economic Civilization.
    - Four Days at the Huntington Rolling Mills.
    - Preparatory Work for Japan (nickel).
    - Mining, Smelting, Refining, Rolling and Applications of Nickel, 1930-1931, (2 copies).
    - Miscellaneous articles on iron, nickel, and steel.
  - General correspondence regarding peppermint leaves and Menthol data., 4 folders. (Box 32)
  - Rice in the Cultural Life of the Japanese, by J. A. Rabbitt.
  - Rice riots in Japan, 1918-1919.
  - Translation of Naoji Suzuki's Bibliography on Rice.
- Data on rice (1938), 5 folders. (Box 33)
  - Rice in Japan, miscellaneous - Folder I. (Box 34)
  - Rice in Japan, miscellaneous - Folder II.
  - Rice in Japan, miscellaneous - Folder III.
  - News clippings on rice in Japan, 1939-1940 - Folder I.
  - News clippings on rice in Japan, 1938-1940 - Folder II. (Box 35)
  - News clippings on rice in Japan, 1939-1940 - Folder III.
  - Miscellaneous articles, agricultural problems, farm machinery, food review.
  - History of the Japanese Tea Industry. (Box 36)
  - Lectures on tea.
  - Newspaper clippings on silk and tea.
  - Materials re iron and steel production in Japan.
  - History, lectures and articles on the Japanese silk industry.
  - Trailing the Moon (poems). (Box 37)
  - War Department, Military Intelligence Division, New York Office, History and Operational Manual (ca. 1944, no author). (RESTRICTED).
  - Rehabilitation of the Mining Industry in the Philippines, by H. Foster Bain.
  - Surveys of the Industries of Japan - 10 volumes, 2 appendices, and 1 supplement as follows: (Box 38)
    - Volume 1 - Textiles.
    - Volume 2 - Chemical Group of the Chemical Industry. (Box 39)
    - Volume 2 (appendix) - Chemical Group of the Chemical Industry.
    - Volume 3 - Dyes, Paints, Oils, Fats, Petroleum, and Toilet Articles. (Box 40)
    - Volume 4 - Cement, Porcelain, Glass, Bricks.
    - Volume 5 - Rubber, Leather, Paper, Celluloid, Explosives, and Matches. (Box 41)
    - Volume 6 - Beverages, Sake, Beer, Soy, Miso, Vinegar, Wines, Liquors and Soft Drinks.
    - Volume 7 -. Canning, Salt, Fisheries, Ice and Refrigeration. (Box 42)
    - Volume 8 - Dairies, Stock Farms, Agricultural Products, Sugar, Confectionery, Tea, and Tobacco. (Box 43)
    - Volume 6,7,8 (appendices) - Food Stuffs. (Box 44)
    - Volume 9 - Mining - Gold, Silver, Platinum, Copper, Lead, Zinc, Iron, Coal, Oil, and Sulphur. (Box 45)
    - Volume 10 - Metals - Iron, Steel, Copper, Zinc, Brass, Lead, Alloys, Castings, Bolts, Nuts, Chains, Plating, etc. (Box 46)
    - Volume 9, 10 (appendices) - Mining and Metals. (Box 47)
    - Supplement A - Trade and Industrial Leaders. (Box 48)
- J. A. Rabbitt - Reports and Surveys: (Box 49)
  - Canton Delta and West River Railways Project, Preliminary Report. October, 1921.
  - Canton City Waterfront and Inner Harbor Improvements. May, 1921.
  - Canton Outer Harbor and Dockyard Development. October 1921. (Box 50)
  - Hakata-Wan Harbor and Daibu Railway Project, 1924.
  - Hakata-Wan Harbor and Daibu Railway Project. Appendix to report, 1924.
  - War Trade Board - economic reports, 1918. (Box 51)
  - Monthly Trade Reports: Japan Trade and Economic Letters, 1934-35.
  - Monthly Trade Reports: Japan Trade and Economic Letters, 1936.
  - Monthly Commercial Reports, 1935. (Box 52)
  - Monthly Commercial Reports, 1936.
  - Monthly Activity Reports - Japanese Bureaus, 1936. (Box 53)
  - Monthly Activity Reports - Japanese Bureaus, 1937.
  - Scientific and Technological Societies of Japan, SCAP report.
  - Japanese Engineering and Scientific Societies, J.A.R. memo #6.
  - Ductile Cast Iron in Japan. Report. (Box 54)
  - Ductile Cast Iron in Japan. Supplement to memo #8. May 1950.
  - Ductile Cast Iron in Japan. Appendix to memo #8 and supplement. June, 1950.
  - Commercial Distribution of Nickel in Japan, 1938.
  - Nickel Deposits in Japan and Korea. 1932-1933.
  - Commercial Distrubution of Nickel in Japan, 1937. (Box 55)
  - Nickel News and reports, 1936-1937.
  - Rotary Steel Process and Casting Machines. (Box 56)
  - Miscellaneous reports on steel.
  - Industrial Reparations Survey of Japan to the United States, February, 1948. C. M. Muchnic.
  - Material on China's iron and steel industry ore sites, coal fields and coal mines.
  - Miscellaneous newsclippings and articles, mainly on Far East metal industries. (Box 57)
  - Miscellaneous personal memorabilia.
  - J. A. Rabbitt, pen and ink sketches. ca. 1895.
  - Miscellaneous personal photographs.
- Guest books (3), 1933-1941 (including photographs of the Japanese residence of the Rabbitts). (Box 58)
- China and Japan photograph album (5) 1895-1930's, as follows: (Box 59)
  - J. A. Rabbitt, 1895-, Rabbitt family and residence ca. 1909, working model of aeroplane, scenes of Japanese countryside and rivers, buildings damaged by the military. (Box 60)
  - China ca. 1920-1923. Chinese graveyard, schoolroom and children, Canton arsenal after being destroyed by General Ma Chai ca. 1921, Shanghai street scenes, 1923.
- Hong Kong and vicinity, 1930's; photographs of rice culture and cultivation in Japan; sketches; photos of tea flowers. (Box 61)
- 1 package of J. A. Rabbitt diplomas, awards, etc. (12). (Box Map cabinet on floor 10)